<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most excellent sermon of the Lordes Supper wherein briefely (and yet plainly yenough [sic]) is liuely set foorth the matter of the Supper of the Lorde Iesus. By Henry Bullinger. Translated out of Frenche, into English by I.T.</title>
            <title>Sermon très-excellent, auquel, en brief et toutes fois assez clairement est représenté au vif tout le fait de la Cène du Seigneur Jésus. English.</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115768</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850986</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1164:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most excellent sermon of the Lordes Supper wherein briefely (and yet plainly yenough [sic]) is liuely set foorth the matter of the Supper of the Lorde Iesus. By Henry Bullinger. Translated out of Frenche, into English by I.T.</title>
                  <title>Sermon très-excellent, auquel, en brief et toutes fois assez clairement est représenté au vif tout le fait de la Cène du Seigneur Jésus. English.</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Dawson and Thomas Gardyner,] nigh vnto vnto [sic] the three Cranes in the Vintree for William Ponsonby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1577]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by J. Tomkys, of Heinrich Bullinger: Sermon très-excellent, auquel, en brief et toutes fois assez clairement est représenté au vif tout le fait de la Cène du Seigneur Jésus.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A most excellent sermon vpon the Lordes Supper.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 4066a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Lord's Supper.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:1"/>
            <p>¶A MOST excellent Sermon of the <hi>Lordes Supper, wherein</hi> briefely (and yet plainly ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) is liuely ſet foorth <hi>the matter of the Supper of the Lorde Ieſus. By Henry Bullinger.</hi>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Tranſlated out of Frenche, into Engliſh, by</hi> I. T.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matthew. 17.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This is my beloued ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare yee hym.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, nigh vnto vnto the three Cranes in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>intree, for William Ponſonby.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:2"/>
            <head>¶To the reuerend Father <hi>in God, Thomas</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Couentrie and Lichfielde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding mee ſelf vnable in all reſpects (reuerend Father) to requite the leaſt benefit receiued at your Lordſhips hands, I haue long intended to preſent your Lordſhip with ſome thing, whereby you might at the leaſte perceyue my grateful mynd, in accepting your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued goodneſſe often vnto me ſhewed. And finding nothing which might pleaſure your Lordſhip, being no leſſe skilful in learnyng, than god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in life, (for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Prou. 27.7.</note> 
               <hi>He that is ful, abhorreth an hony combe.</hi>) I thought I coulde not better pleaſe you, which are no leſſe carefull for the Chriſtian Congregation, than is the Father for
<pb facs="tcp:16237:3"/> his children, than by taking in hande ſome ſuch matter, wherby I mee ſelfe might be well occupied, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an common Wealth edified, and God glorified. For this cauſe, that the vnlearned, not onely of your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe, but alſo of all places els in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, which are deſtitute of painfull Preachers of Gods woord, (for who knoweth not, that the labourers in Gods Vineyarde be verye fewe?) might be inſtructed, at the leaſte by reading, in the true profeſsion of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, I haue preſumed to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late foorth of Frenche, a Sermon of the Lordes Supper, made by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and graue Father, mayſter <hi>Henry Bullinger.</hi> Neither dyd I perceyue, whereby I might more profit all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than by handelyng the Lordes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which yerely and often ought to be receyued of al men, nor wherein I
<pb facs="tcp:16237:3"/> might better ſerue my carnall and tranſitory countrey, than in ſetting foorth that foode, whereby we are fed to out ſpirituall and euerlaſting countrey. For if we ought to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile painefully for the foode of the body, (according to the admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle <hi>Saint Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>That if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would not worke, the ſame ſhould not eate:</hi>) whiche although we haue in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, mainteyneth vs not alwayes, being by ſyn made ſubiect to death, howe much more painefull ought we to be for the atchieuing of the foode of the ſoule, Chriſte Ieſus, which is the bread of life, wherof if we eate by faith, we ſhall not die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by grace made partakers of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life? Wheras there be many, which haue learnedly, &amp; godly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled this argument, I am moued to thinke my labour beſt beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb facs="tcp:16237:4"/> this authour, becauſe there is none which I haue read, that dooth in ſo briefe a ſumme, in my ſimple iudgement, more plainly ſet foorth the doctrine of the Lordes Supper, to the comfort of the profeſſours of the Goſpel, or more ſenſibly diſcloſe the errours thruſt into the Church of God, concernyng; the ſame, to the griefe of the aduerſaries of the truth: both the which poyntes he hath ſo aptly handled, that I knowe not in whether he hath vſed more facilitie. It may be, that ſome, which haue not only trauailed of purpoſe into Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (the hithermoſt coaſtes whereof I neuer ſaw) there to learne the french tongue, but alſo at home haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſtudied to attayne the finenes of the Engliſhe tongue, (wherein I confeſſe I was neuer curious,) might haue tranſlated this Sermon,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:4"/> much more finely, than by me it is. I enuie not their skill, neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine I their trauaile. I haue done myne indeuour, ſo neare as I could, to vſe my ſelfe like a faithful Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretour, in yeelding the ſenſe of the Authour truely and yet in ſuch ſort, as beſt might be vnderſtood by the vnlearned Reader. Touchyng the teſtimonies of holy Scripture, alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by this authour in this Sermon, I haue thought good rather to ſet them down after the laſt tranſlation of the Bible, ſet foorth by aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, than to tranſlate them foorth of the French, that I might the rather hereby cut of the cauilles of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of the truth, whith they are woont to make vpon the diuerſitie of Tranſlations. And that the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Readers, if it ſhal pleaſe them to conferre the Teſtimonies with the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:5"/> Text, may the more eaſily find forth the ſame, I haue quoted in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent both chapter and verſe, whence they are taken.</p>
            <p>Thus, haue I yeelded vnto your Lordſhip, the cauſes of my bold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, with the order of the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deling of the ſame, which if it may pleaſe God to bleſſe with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Readers knowledge, I haue my deſire. God long preſerue your Lordſhip, to the comforte of his Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhyppes <hi>to commaund,</hi> I. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:5"/>
            <head>¶ A Sermon of the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of our Lorde Ieſus</hi> Chriſte the Sonne of God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul</hi> alſo the veſſel of election, and Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and perfectly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed the holy and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Supper of our Lorde and Redeemer Ieſus Chriſt, in theſe wordes:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the Euen was come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.20. Mar. 14.22. 1. Cor. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame night in which Ieſus was betrayed, he ſate downe with the twelue. And as they dyd eate, Ieſus, when he had taken bread, and geuen thankes, brake (it,) and gaue it to his Diſciples, ſaying: Take yee, eate yee, This is my body which is broken<note place="margin">Or giuen.</note> for you, This doo in the remembrance of me. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo when he had ſupped, he tooke the Cuppe, and when he had geuen thankes, he gaue it to them, ſaying: Drinke ye all of it, and they all dranke of it. Then he ſaide to them, This is my bloud of the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:6"/>
            <p>Saint <hi>Luke</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> haue:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.20. 1. Cor. 11.25.</note>
               <hi>This Cuppe is the newe Testament in my bloud, which is ſhedde for you, and for many, for the remiſſion of ſinnes. As often as you ſhall doo this, doo it in remembrance of me. For as often as yee eate this beead, and drinke this Cuppe, yee doo ſhewe the Lordes death tyll he come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal poyntes of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note>In the holy and myſticall Supper of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, we muſt not onely conſider the woordes of the Inſtitution preſently recited, but alſo we muſte here ioyne the things going before, with thoſe whiche come after: as ſuch, whereby the whole myſterie is more clearely and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſet foorth.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we muſt conſider the doctrine which the Lord taught his Diſciples in the Supper. Secondly, what he did, and how he inſtituted this Supper: that is to ſay, howe the Lord celebrated it, and ordeyned it to be celebrated by the Church, vnto the ende of the world.</p>
            <p>Finally, of what ſort the diſciples were in this ſupper, and how they behaued them
<pb facs="tcp:16237:6"/> ſelues therein: that we may learne hereby, howe we ought to behaue our ſelues in ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating this moſt holy banquet, and alſo that by the declaration of all theſe poynts, we may vnderſtand truely what the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Supper of the Lord is: that is to ſay, (ſpeaking in the firſt place, of the ſumme of the matter, although it be inwrapped in ſhadowes and figures, and propoſing the whole matter, as it were to be beholden with one onely ſight) that it is a ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Ceremonie, or an holy action,<note place="margin">What the myſtical ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord is.</note> ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the Churche, by Ieſus Chriſte, our Lord, Redemer, and high Prieſt, wherby, in ſetting before vs in this Banquet, the bread and the wine, being myſtical tokens and pledges, he commendeth vnto vs in like maner his doctrine, and alſo maketh vs a full promiſe of euerlaſting life, the which (in geuing his bodye to death, and ſhedding his bloud) he hath prepared for vs: and offered them vnto vs, to be recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by faith, in liuely meate and drinke, and by this certification he ratifieth it vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, he repreſenteth or ſignifieth by theſe tokens and pledges, reneweth, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16237:7"/> as it were ſetteth before our ſenſes his gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or benefites, which the faithful receiue. Alſo he gathereth together viſibly his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes into the companie and vnitie of his body: finally he confirmeth vnto vs the remembrance of his death and paſſion, and of our redemption, admoniſhing vs in the meane ſeaſon of our dutie, which is chiefely to yelde him prayſe and thankes giuyng.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of what fort the doctrine of our Lorde in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is.</note>Touching the doctrine, as it is euerye where ſo is it alſo heere: that is to ſaye, a thing ſo excellent, that it ſurmounteth all the reſt, which doctrine, although it be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and moſt copious, yet is it ſuch, as may be gathered into certaine and a fewe Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the doctrine of our Lord. The ende of the Supper.</note>For the firſt and chiefeſt matter, which it handleth at large and moſt euidently, is the principall poynt of our Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the ende of our myſticall Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: that is to ſay, that the Lorde our God of his meere grace and mercy taking pitie of mankind, ſent into the worlde for the ſaluation of the faithfull, his onely ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who by his death
<pb facs="tcp:16237:7"/> hath purged vs from all our ſinnes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vs from death, from hell, and from Satan, and made vs heires of life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
            <p>And for ſo much as in this poynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth chiefely all the matter of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he commendeth vnto vs, and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this thing in many ſortes and diuerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the ende that we ſhoulde not forget him, or lightly regarde him, but that he myght ſhewe himſelfe cleerely vnto the faythfull for euer, as a moſt cleare lyght, which myght ſhyne vnto them and lighten them.</p>
            <p>Moreouer he figureth, propoſeth, and commendeth vnto vs, vnder moſt apt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and ſhadowes, this moſt excellent part of doctrine.</p>
            <p>For in the beginning of the Supper,<note place="margin">The Lorde waſheth his diſciples feete.</note> the Lorde waſhed his diſciples feete. By the which acte, (after that he had lyuely declared vnto them a great humilitie of hart, with charitie, and affection of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeruice, and of all kinde of dutifull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour one toward another,) we reade, that the Lorde ſayde vnto Peter, which
<pb facs="tcp:16237:8"/> gayneſayd him:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.8.</note>
               <hi>If I waſhe thee not, thou hast no part with me,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſtraight way afterward:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.10</note>
               <hi>He which is waſhed, needeth not ſaue to waſhe his feete, but is cleane euery whit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby we gather, that the Lorde hath taught hereby, that they, which are once receyued to the fauour of God, and purged by the bloud of the Sonne of God, receyued by fayth, are fully iuſtified.</p>
            <p>But bycauſe they, which are iuſtifyed, ſo long as they lyue in this world, haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities in their fleſhe, wherewyth they are after a ſort ſoulied, as be the feete of them, which are waſhed with muddy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he ſignifieth, that they ſhould clenſe theſe ſpottes by continuall repentance. Here vnto agreeth the worthy ſaying of the holy Apoſtle:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom 8.</note>
               <hi>There is then no damnation to them, which are in Christ Ieſu, which walke not after the fleſhe, but after the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Lorde eateth with his diſciples the Paſcal Lambe.</note>Agayne the Lorde ſetteth before our eyes our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, obtained by his death when he eateth with a great deſire wyth
<pb facs="tcp:16237:8"/> his Diſciples the Paſcall Lambe beyng offered vp. For we knowe, that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lambe of God, which taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde, and that Chriſt our Paſſeouer is offered vp, and that the ſprinklyng of his bloud ſtayeth and keepeth farre from vs the deſtroying Angell. Alſo that he clenſeth our ſinnes, and refreſheth vs with ſpirituall drinke, guideth vs to eternall lyfe, and maketh his father pacifyed with vs, who, were it not for this, would ſtill be angry agaynſt our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Moreouer he commendeth vnto vs the myſterie of our redemption, by the bread and wine holily inſtituted, for ſignes and Sacramentes of his bodye deliuered to death, and of his bloud ſhed for vs, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that we neuer forget him. Beſides this, he hath not onely commended vnto vs this principall point of our ſaluation in parables and figures, but alſo hath expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it vnto vs moſt manifeſtly in cleere and euident woordes,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.2.</note> as when he ſayth plainely, that many manſions (that is to ſay, ſufficient dwelling places) are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:9"/> with his heauenly father, to receiue all the elect, and that he departeth hence, that by his death, he myght open the heauenly dwellings, to bring in thether his faythful ſeruauntes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Io. 14.3.</note>
               <hi>For I will receiue you (euen) vnto my ſelfe, that where I am, there maye ye be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And agayne he ſayth,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Io. 14.6.</note>
               <hi>I am the way, and the truth, and the life: no man commeth vnto the father but by me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Io. 15.3.</note>
               <hi>Nowe are ye cleane through the word, which I haue ſpoken vnto you. Byde in me, and I in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I omit here purpoſely many ſuch lyke things: for you haue ſufficiently vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode by that which wee haue alledged, with what diligence, and howe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and aptly, he hath expounded and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs in his doctrine (the which often in his Supper he repeated to hys Diſciples) the principall point of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond article.</note>Nowe for ſo much as the doctrine of
<pb facs="tcp:16237:9"/> our Lord Ieſus Chriſt doth not only ſhew vnto vs our redemption,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The ſeconde Article.</p>
                  <p>The Lorde teacheth vs alſo repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Supper.</p>
               </note> and teacheth that faith in Chriſt, which truely iuſtifieth, but alſo inſtructed vs to repentaunce, and to a graue and earneſt accuſation of all our miſdeedes, a man may finde a ſingular diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of all this matter in this Supper. And becauſe there be two ſortes of men, the one altogether hypocriticall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull, wherof <hi>Iudas Iſcariot</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed our Sauiour, is the true patterne: and the other righteous, pure, perfect, and faithful, neuertheleſſe laden and burdened with vices and ſinnes, the which the other Diſciples of our Lord doo repreſent: the Lorde in the beginnyng addreſſeth his ſpeache to <hi>Iudas,</hi> and admoniſheth hym grauely, reproueth hym, and toucheth him nearely, threatening hym with euerlaſting deſtruction: Conſequently, he repreſſeth his Diſciples reaſonyng among them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, who ſhould be greateſt: he confirmeth, comforteth, and ſtrengtheneth the weake, the fearefull, and ready to fall.</p>
            <p>Alſo he aduertiſeth them of their gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous fall, exhorting them after their fall,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:10"/> to repentance, in ſetting before them the example of <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom he ſaid:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.31.</note>
               <hi>Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired to ſift you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the reſt which is to be read in the .22. of S. Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the faithfull ſhould do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to the Supper.</note>Out of all the which things we maye gather, that in al the Sermons which are to be made to the people, both before the Supper, and in the Supper, wherby they are to prepare them ſelues thereunto, it is neceſſary that the firſt part be an earneſt accuſation of the former diſordered and wicked life, with a moſt diligent admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to repentance: to the ende that al may know them ſelues, and acknowledge their ſinnes, that they may confeſſe them ſelues to God purely in their hartes, that they may aſke full pardon of the high prieſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and that they may change their filthy and vngodly life, into an honeſt and godly life, and alſo that they may through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent them ſelues, and be aſhamed of their ſinnes committed, and laſtly, that they may all by ſtedfaſt faith refourme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and beholde the grace of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:10"/>
            <p>Hereunto without doubt apperteineth the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let a man examine hym ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo let hym eate of this bread, and drinke of this Cuppe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, the doctrine of repentaunce may not ceaſe after the Supper. For it muſt often be repeated vnto men, that they keepe them ſelues from committing any thing vnwoorthy hym, whoſe members they be made in the holye Church.</p>
            <p>This ſelfe ſame doctrine of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The thirde article.</p>
                  <p>The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord touching cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie, paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. &amp;c.</p>
               </note> bringeth to our remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fayth and repentaunce, mutuall loue and charitie, the which without ceaſing, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of all thoſe, who being the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſte, are made in like manner, brethren of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche cal vpon his name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By this ſhall all men knowe</hi> (ſaith the Lorde) <hi>that yee are my Diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>if yee haue loue together, as I haue loued you. This is my commaundement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>that ye loue together, as I haue loued you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And many other things to the like effect.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, he teacheth vs conſtancie in true faith, and pacience in aduerſities
<pb facs="tcp:16237:11"/> and afflictions, declaryng the griefes which the faythfull muſt ſuffer in this world, for Ieſus Chriſt. The doctrine of the Lorde is manifeſt in <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> in the xv. and .xvi. chapters. There he exhorteth the faithfull to continue firme and faſt in hym, by a ſure hope, and not to be plucked thence by any meanes. Alſo he admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them, that in his name, (as in the name of the only and true Mediator) they call vpon God without ceaſſyng. In ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he promiſeth them moſt certaine and moſt ready helpe. By the which things we learne to exact the whole, according to the doctrine of the Euangeliſts and of the Churche, of all them which be partakers of the Lordes Supper. That is to wyt, that they be in loue and charitie one with another, that they be conſtant in faith, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in afflictions, which they ſuffer for Ieſus Chriſt: and finally, that they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtedfaſt in hope, and that they ſeparate not them ſelues from Chriſte, and all his members, to commyt them ſelues ouer to to ſtraunge Religions: and moreouer, that they continue in prayers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:11"/>
            <p>To be briefe,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The fourth Article.</p>
                  <p>The Lordes doctrine of his body, and his ſpirit.</p>
               </note> there is nothing which the Lord repeateth more diligently, nor more often vnto his Diſciples, in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon which he made vnto them after the Supper, than this: That he woulde no longer be neither with them, nor with his Church, bodyly, and yet notwithſtandyng that he would not forſake his in any thing, but that he would alwayes be carefull for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I wyl pray the Father</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and he ſhall giue you another Comforter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.16.</note> 
               <hi>that he may bide with you for euer, <hi>(euen)</hi> the ſpirit of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>(and) <hi>he ſhal teach you all things, and bring al things to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, whatſoeuer I haue ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is expedient for you, that I goe away:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>for if I goe not away, that comforter wyll not come vnto you: but if I depart, I wyll ſende hym vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the reſt which foloweth in the .xvi. of <hi>ſaint Iohn:</hi> Whereby we gather ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, that this doctrine ought to be continuall in the Churche, the which muſt be often tymes inculcated, and brought to
<pb facs="tcp:16237:12"/> mynd in the Supper of the Lorde, that the church of Chriſt may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that thoſe things which are ſpoken of the preſence of the Lord, in the church, and of the eating of hym, muſt not be expounded carnally, nor corporally, but ſpiritually: and that the heauenly foode eaten ſpiritually, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth.</p>
            <p>Hytherto I haue intreated briefely of the diuers, plentiful, and wholeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, propoſed to his diſciples in his myſtical Supper, &amp; deliuered by him, to be alwaies ſet forth in his ſupper to his church, vntyl the worlds ende. And now we come to the other part of this Sermon, to ſhewe with ſuche breuitie and facilitie, as poſſibly we may, not onely that which the Lorde ſpake, but alſo that which he dyd: that is to ſay, how he inſtituted this ceremoniall ſupper (if it may ſo be called) and howe the Sonne of God hym ſelfe, hauyng diſtributed the breade and the wine, celebrated the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and inſtituted it to be celebrated in his Churche, vntyl the ende of the worlde.</p>
            <p>This hath been from the beginning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:12"/> and the Lorde our God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vſed to ioyne ſignes to his promiſe or woord,<note place="margin">A briefe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; of the reaſon of the ſame.</note> whereby he bringeth to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce his great and free benefites beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppon men before, or to be beſtowed vppon them after, by the which ſignes he gathereth men together into one compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, wherein thoſe benefites may be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſolemnly by the woorde of God, and that alſo they may (as a man woulde ſay) be renued and imprinted perpetually in their memorie. And moreouer, that ſuch graces may be ſet foorth to our viewe, by pledges and ſignes to be beholden of vs, and to bee faſtened more deepely in our hartes. Alſo, that they may be confirmed by a witneſſe, and that the faithfull maye vnderſtande what it is, that the Lorde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth againe at their handes, &amp; alſo what the duties &amp; exerciſes of godlynes are.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the ſignes take the names of the things ſignified, &amp; are called moſte certaine and true ſeales, markes, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes of the promiſes and benefites of God, becauſe they repreſent them, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, bring them to remembrance, and
<pb facs="tcp:16237:13"/> ſeale them according to their propertie. Theſe therfore conſiſt in the word of God, by the thing ſignified, through the ſigne or Symbol, which is the outward thing ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the woorde of God.</p>
            <p>Such were the Sacramentes of the auncient people, as the Paſſeouer, the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſacrifices of the Fathers, inſtituted partly for the acknowledging, callyng to remembraunce, and ſetting foorth of Gods benefites: partly to ſignifie, that Chriſt ſhould come, and dye, by whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent death, mankinde ſhoulde be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from euerlaſting death: the which moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and free benefite for all ages was bountifully beſtowed in Chriſt vpon the faithfull, in theſe latter tymes.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we muſt not onely conſider in ſuch holy Sacramentes or Symbols, the outward cuſtome and facion of doyng, I meane the maner of eating, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſing, neither yet the things ſet before our corporall eyes, but much rather ought we by the contemplation of the ſigne, (being inſtructed by his woorde, and inwardly
<pb facs="tcp:16237:13"/> lightened by the holy Ghoſt) to lift vp our ſelues, and to pierce vnto the conſideration and ful fruition of the ſpiritual things ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, whereof commeth greate profite, if they be receiued by faith.</p>
            <p>They which beholde onely the outward cuſtome and facion of the Sacramentes of the olde Fathers, without the woorde, faith, and the inwarde lightenyng of the ſpirite, and doo conſider none other thing in the Paſcal ſupper, nor in the ſacrifices of the Fathers, but that which we beholde outwardly with our eyes, what difference thinke you, may they put betweene thoſe things, and a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> banquet, or a ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherin the beaſtes are ſlaine before the bouchers table, euen in ſuch ſort as vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the holy Aultar? Contrarily, it wyll ſeeme to our fleſhe, that theſe holy things haue no maieſtie at all, but that they be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be mocked at. For this cauſe, we reade, that the moſt holy and moſt wiſe Prophetes of God dyd greatly reproue them, which eſteemed the ſacrifices by the outward appearance onely, without faith, and the ſpirit, ſaying:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.12. Iere. 7.20.</note>
               <hi>Who hath required this at your handes? Heape vp your burnt offerings with your ſacrifices, and eate the fleſhe. For when I brought your Fathers foorth of Egypt, I ſpake no woorde vnto them of burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and ſacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſt is in <hi>Ieremie</hi> the ſeuenth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">After that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the auncient Fathers had taken an end among the ancient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the new ſacraments were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the new people.</note>Nowe becauſe all the ſacramentes of the auncient Fathers dyd promiſe, that Chriſt ſhould come, and redeeme his elect, and alſo conſidering that the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt is already come into the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing geuen of his Father for the ſaluation of all the faithful, it had been very vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the ſignes ſhoulde continue in the church, which ſhould witneſſe, that Chriſt ſhould come, who already was come.</p>
            <p>Wherefore Chriſt, after that he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed the Symboles, and ceremonies of the auncient fathers, to wyt, Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the feaſt of the Paſſeouer, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, in ſtead of Circumciſion, placed Baptiſme, and in ſtead of the Sacrifices, and of the Paſcall Supper, ordeyned his myſticall Supper, for a perpetual ſigne,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:14"/> and vnchaungeable memorial of his body yeelded vp, and geuen to the death, and of his bloud ſhedde.</p>
            <p>Therefore you muſt not only regarde in this our miſticall ſupper, the ſigne, the faſhion of dooing, and the outward act, but rather the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>The ſymboll or the ſigne in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is the breade and wine, and the holy banquet it ſelfe, and the miſticall action, which Ieſus Chriſt hath geuen vs. The thing ſignified, is the body of our Lord deliuered for vs, and his bloud ſhedde for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and the paſſion of the Lord it ſelfe, and the remembrance thereof, and our redemption which enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This doo</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The companie therfore of the faythful aſſemble them ſelues togeather to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the miſteries of Chriſt. In the which according to the auncient cuſtome, the ſimbols of bread and of wine, borrowe the names of the things ſignified, and be called the body and the bloud of the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:16237:15"/> Ieſus. Hereby are we called backe from viſible things to behold heauenly things, which are ſpiritually communicated vnto vs.</p>
            <p>For if thou behold onely the breaking of the breade, and the diſtribution of the the cuppe, with the brotherly feaſt: and if thou knowe not what this breade is, what this wine is, and what things they repreſent vnto vs, in refreſhing our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie therewith, this Supper will not ſeeme to differ much from a common ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The ſacrament therefore of Ieſus Chriſt deliuered to death and of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in lyke manner our redemption, is deliuered here vnto vs. And that we may the better vnderſtand theſe things, we wil proceed in ſearching out through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which the Lord did in this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that which he commaunded vs to doo.</p>
            <p>It is not needefull that I be tedious vnto you in ſpeaking more of the forme &amp; maner of the Inſtitution of the Supper:<note place="margin">Of the forme and maner of giuyng of thankes in the Lordes Supper.</note> for the Lorde our Sauiour inſtituted it, and he did not inſtitute the Maſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:15"/>
            <p>And if the Maſſe ſeeme vnto any to be worthy of commendation, price, and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, becauſe it was ordeyned by the auncient Popes of Rome: howe muche more, I beſeeche you, ought the Supper to be renoumed and eſteemed, which was inſtituted by the great and onely prieſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, before all Popes, and before Rome had receyued the faith from Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, it is moſt certaine, and out of all controuerſie, that the Lord ordeyned this forme, and none other. And for this cauſe we reade, that <hi>ſaint Paul</hi> Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſaid:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which I deliuered vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely the Euangeliſtes and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles are witneſſes, that the Lord ſaid often tymes: <hi>This doo yee, <hi>(I ſay)</hi> this doo yee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24. &amp; 25.</note> 
               <hi>this doo yee:</hi> that is to ſay, This which you ſee me firſt doo. We haue then the expreſſe commaundement of God, and the cleare woorde, whereunto not without cauſe we are obedient: We haue a famous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example, which if we ſhould not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb facs="tcp:16237:16"/> we ſhould woorthily be called tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors. And truely that which is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs by the Sonne of God hymſelf, which is the wiſedome of the Father, and the light of al the world, deſerueth well to be preferred before the aucthoritie of the moſt excellent perſonage of the world.</p>
            <p>And if the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient Fathers be in great eſtimation among you, whoſe aucthoritie, knowledge, holyneſſe, and auncientneſſe hath woonne vnto them a great renoume, in ſo much that in conſideration of them, the Maſſe is taken to be an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thing, ought not the Apoſtles, the Father of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be much more eſteemed of you, who in holyneſſe and learnyng, and in all things are to be preferred before all men, and before all that is in the worlde? They knewe not what the Maſſe ment, but they celebrated the Supper in the ſame forme as the Goſpell here teacheth vs. For as much then as the Maſſe was as it were vnknowen vnto the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient Fathers them ſelues, as we ſaid, let vs, ſetting it apart, approch to the Supper of the Lorde, and let the Inſtitution of the Sonne of God
<pb facs="tcp:16237:16"/> pleaſe vs. Let vs thinke, that without the word of God, there is no holyneſſe.<note place="margin">That which ſwarueth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worde of God, is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which repugneth the ordinaunce of God, and is not done, as God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, may rightly be called curſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege. Theſe things are confirmed by the aucthoritie of God and man. For the Lord ſaith in his Lawe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſoeuer offereth not at the doore of the Tabernacle, an offring vnto the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit. 17.4.</hi> This teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the ſenſe of the place whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is taken.</note> 
               <hi>ſhalbe giltie of bloud, and ſhal periſh, as if he had ſhed bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider, wherfore in the hiſtories of the kynges, the high places are reiected with ſo great indignation. And in like manner <hi>Paul</hi> accurſeth, and pronounceth euery thyng curſed, which agreeth not with the Goſpell, or which is contrarye thereunto.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo the Martyr ſaith, that euery thing which is deuiſed by mans madneſſe, to breake Gods ordinaunce, is adulterous, wicked, and full of ſacrilege. In his firſt and ſeconde booke of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 3.</note> 
               <hi>We ought not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the cuſtome of man, but the truth
<pb facs="tcp:16237:17"/> of God, for ſo much as God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and ſayth by <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 29.13. Mark. 7.7.</note>
               <hi>In vayne doo they worſhippe me, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching doctrines the commaundementes of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For if in the ſacrifice which is Chriſt, none but Chriſt only is to be follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, then verely ought we to heare and doo that which Chriſt did, and which hee commaunded to be done, conſidering that he himſelfe ſayth in his Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 15.14. &amp; 15.</note>
               <hi>Ye are my friendes if ye doo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I commaund you. Hencefoorth call I not you ſeruants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that Chriſt onely ought to be heard, the Father alſo beareth witnes from heauen, ſaying:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mart. 17; 5.</note>
               <hi>This is my beloued ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare yee hym.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore if Chriſte onely be to be hearde, we muſt no tregard, what any before vs hath ſuppoſed ſhoulde be done, but what Chriſt, who is before al men, dyd firſt.</hi> Al this ſaith <hi>S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:17"/>
            <p>Therefore let vs goe foreward to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine diligently that, which the Lord dyd before all, and that which he hath inioyned vs to doo by his commaundement and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, yea and inculcated, and often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Ieſus hauing partly ended the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome admonitions, tooke bread,<note place="margin">He taketh the bread.</note> and the cuppe alſo, he tooke (I ſay) of the breade which then was vpon the table of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Supper. He tooke alſo of the wyne. Nowe my brethren, when we heare theſe things, let not the ſimplicitie of our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, without pompe, without worldly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, and without any great ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ingender in vs a contempt thereef. For our lord celebrating theſe holy things with his Diſciples, had on but comely and common apparell. There was not ſeene any <hi>Aaronical</hi> attyre, nor any Ephod, nor any prieſtly veſtures. There was neither glittering of gold, nor of ſyluer. Neither was there to be ſeene any precious ſtones. Let vs therefore eſteeme all theſe thyngs by the authour thereof, I meane, by the ſonne of God, who is the wiſedome of the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:18"/> Father, whom ſince this ſimplicitie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it ought alſo to pleaſe thee, ſeeing that if he would, he could haue giuen to all this matter, a forme much more famous and precious, then all the things of this world. And alſo remember the wordes of <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaying to <hi>Saul:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of the ſupper are ſimple, and without pompe.</note>
               <hi>To obey, is better then Sacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Verily our Lorde hath taken away the painfull ceremonies of the lawe, and hath inſtituted a newe forme, without labour or ſumptuouſneſſe, and eaſie to be furniſhed. Alſo, all things apperteynyng to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, haue more efficacie of the ſpirit, and of ſpirituall vertue, than of ſhewe, as alſo they are more ſimple, and eaſie to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, than are the figures and ceremonies of the Lawe. And <hi>Lactantius</hi> an aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Authour, in the ſixt booke, and fiue and twenty chapter of his <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> ſaith: <hi>He which thinketh that God hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in garmentes, precious ſtones, and other things which are greatly ſet by, is vtterly ignorant what God is. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That more is, this ſimple Inſtitution is the true bleſſyng and conſecration of the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:18"/> Supper, hauing the woorde of God for an expreſſe marke and commaundement.</p>
            <p>Neyther muſt we here depend of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, neyther looke for the breathing of a Prieſt conſecrated by a Biſhop, recityng diſtinctly the fiue woordes of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thereby takyng vpon hym to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate the Sacrament. For the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of our Lord reſtraineth yet effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually her vertue and efficacie teſtified by the woorde of truth, and endureth ſtyll, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng euen nowe full force in our celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: wherin we doo none other thing, but that which he hymſelfe dyd, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be done.</p>
            <p>We haue then yet hytherto the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of the Lorde, and we haue nothing to doo with theſe Maſſemumblers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we celebrate the ſupper of the Lord, and a moſt ſtraunge Supper. For euen nowe we receyue the whole from the very handes of Chriſte, by the miniſterie of a lawful and Eccleſiaſticall Miniſter. To be briefe, we doo iuſtly eſteeme this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratyng and bleſſyng of our high Prieſte Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of God, more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:16237:19"/> than the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration of all Biſhops, which hath no teſtimonie nor confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the woord of God, and for this cauſe we greatly abhorre it.</p>
            <p>After this, the Lorde<note place="margin">The fiſte Article. The Lorde gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes and bleſſed.</note> gaue thankes: let vs therefore geue thankes to God the Father alſo.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Marke</hi> 14.22.</note> He bleſſed: and let vs bleſſe hym alſo in like maner.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the other Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt expoundeth this bleſſyng, by geuyng of thankes. Euen ſo is there often tymes afterwarde mention made thereof. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no marueile if the auncient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue geuen it eſpecially the name of <hi>Euchariſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes geuyng.</note> (that is to ſay, <hi>Thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing)</hi> although beſides this, it haue diuers other names. For the which cauſe they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it <hi>A Supper, a Sacrifice.</hi> For inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, prayſe, and geuyng of thankes, is a Sacrifice acceptable vnto God: But the fleſhe and the bloud of the Lord, are not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Maſſe eftſoones for the ſinnes of the quicke and the dead. For ſince they haue been once offered, they retayne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes their vertue for the ſaluation of the faythfull.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:19"/>
            <p>Moreouer, the Lord<note place="margin">The ſixte Article. The Lorde brake the bread. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. The brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of bread.</note> brake the breade which he tooke, and which he bleſſed, or ouer the which he gaue thankes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the auncient writers named the whole holy miſterie, by this parte of the action thereof, <hi>the breaking of bread.</hi> Let vs then breake the bread hauing receyued it at the Miniſters handes, or rather let vs receyue it being broken by him. The hand ſinneth not here by touching, for ſo much as neyther the tongue nor the mouth which likewiſe touch the ſame, doo ſinne any whit at all. Superſtition ſayth, <hi>Taſt it not, touch it not.</hi> But the breaking of the bread bringeth to our remembrance the paſſion of the Lord. For that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> vttereth thus:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>Which is broken for you.</hi> Saint <hi>Luke</hi> vttereth thus.<note place="margin">Luke 22.18.</note> 
               <hi>Which is geuen for you.</hi> Admoniſhing vs alſo of our vnitie and dutie. Becauſe we which are many<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.17.</note> make one body, for ſo much as we are all partakers of one bread, as the Apoſtle expoundeth this miſterie in the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> the tenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the Lord<note place="margin">Matt. 26.26. Marke 14.22. Luke 22.19.</note> gaue vnto his
<pb facs="tcp:16237:20"/> Diſciples the bread being broken, and commaunded them to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 84.22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. He gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing broken.</note> eate. And for this cauſe the miniſters ought in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord to geue the bread vnto the faithfull people, that they may eate it. And verely the Diſciples in the firſt Supper tooke the bread which was geuen them, and did eate it. Let vs therefore doo the lyke. Neyther muſt we incloſe it in the cloſeds pixes, or boxes, neither ought we to beare it this way and that way for a ſhew, neyther may we woorſhip it bowing our knees, in ſinging this Hymne. <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ergò Sacramentum veneremur cernui</hi>) That is to ſay, <hi>Let vs woorſhip ſo great a ſacrament bowing our ſelues down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> The Lorde in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to his Apoſtles hath taughte vs nothing touching theſe matters. For theſe things were ordayned long tyme after, by the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> and their miniſters,<note place="margin">Dan. 12.11.</note> that that which was foreſpoken by <hi>Daniell</hi> and by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt myght be accompliſhed.<note place="margin">Math. 24.15.</note> Nowe becauſe hee gaue them breade to eate, he expoundeth foorthwith that
<pb facs="tcp:16237:20"/> which is ſignified by this bread, leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture any ſhould lyghtly eſteeme this bread, and make as litle accompte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as of vſuall and common bread: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayth he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is my body which is geuen for you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Which kinde of ſpeech is altogeather like vnto that of the paſcall Supper, that is to ſay:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This is my body. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.22 <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.11</note>
               <hi>Of this manner ſhall ye eate it: with your loynes girded, and your ſhoes on your feete, and your ſtaffe in your hand, and ye ſhall eate it in hast: For it is the Lordes<note place="margin">In Hebrue, <hi>Peſa,</hi> that is to ſay, a Paſſage.</note> Paſſouer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euen ſo dooth the Lord ſpeake in this place in lyke ſort:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take ye, eate ye: this is my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit this ſpeech is ſacramentall and miſticall:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26 <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.22 The bread is not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the ſubſtance of the bodye of Chriſt.</note> wherefore it ought to be expounded ſimbollycally and according to the meaning. For the breade is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſigne, or pledge of the body of Chriſt. And truely the auncient Doctours of the Churche haue ſo expounded theſe wordes of our Lord. And in deede we doo not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe any newe matter, in ſaying, that the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:21"/> bread ſignifieth the body of Chriſte: For we haue els where ſhewed at large, that the auncient Interpreters of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as wel Greekes as Latines, haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this expoſition.</p>
            <p>Alſo we haue geuen you to vnderſtande by many euident reaſons, that theſe words of our Lord:<note place="margin">Matt. 26.26. Marke 14.22. 1. Cor. 11.24. Mat 26.26. Marke 14.24.</note> 
               <hi>This is my body,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.26. Marke 14.22. 1. Cor. 11.24. Mat 26.26. Marke 14.24.</note> This is my bloud,</hi> ought not to be taken accordyng to the groſſe literall ſenſe, but to be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded myſtically, or ſacramentally. For the bread remayneth in his ſubſtance, and is not chaunged into the ſubſtance of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.<note place="margin">The proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.</note> In like maner the naturall body of Ieſus Chriſt (the which being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen once for vs, and rayſed from death, is aſcended into heauen) is not hyd nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed vnder the kinde or forme of bread. For the Angels of God, ſpeakyng of this body, beare witneſſe thereof, and ſay:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Actes 1.11.</note>
               <hi>This ſame Ieſus which is taken vp from you into heauen, ſhall ſo come, euen as you haue ſeene hym goe into heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like maner <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Actes 3.21.</note>
               <hi>The heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt receiue Ieſus Chriſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl the tyme that all things be reſtored. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth alſo:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt after he hath offered one ſacrifice for ſinnes, is ſet down for euer on the right hand of God, from hencefoorth tarying tyll his foes be made his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherfore, we reade that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> writing to <hi>Dardanus,</hi> ſaid rightly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the Scriptures: <hi>Chriſt, as he is God, is all wholy preſent in euerye place, but, accordyng to the meaſure &amp; propertie of a true bodye, he hath his place in ſome one place of heauen. He hath giuen immortalitie to his body</hi> (in the glorification therof.) <hi>After this forme he is not to be thought to be diffuſed and ſpread abrode euery where. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt take good heede, that we doo not ſo affirme the Diuinitie of the man</hi> (Chriſte) <hi>that wee take awaye the truth of</hi> (his) <hi>body. For one perſon is God and man, and one Chriſte Ieſus is both two, being euery where, in that he is God: but being in heauen, in that he is Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, and this Authour hath left in his
<pb facs="tcp:16237:22"/> bookes, theſe things, and many other like, both Catholique, and according to the true ſenſe of the Scripture, agreeable to this matter. Moreouer, the Catholique veritie ſuffereth vs not to faine, that Chriſt hath two bodyes. But if thou take the woordes of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Math. 26.26. Mark. 14.22. Luke. 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> after the Letter, <hi>This is my body:</hi> without doubt the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body of the Lorde being ſet at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with his Diſciples, gaue vnto them alſo, I knowe not what other body: for he could not geue hym ſelf with his own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vnto his Diſciples. Therefore with his true body, and with his handes, he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto his Diſciples, the Sacrament of his onely bodye. Hereuppon it foloweth, that the faythfull acknowledging the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and miſterie, receiue with their mouth, the ſacramental bread of his body: but with the mouth of the ſpirit, they eate the very body of the Lord.<note place="margin">How we eate the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt. Io. 6. from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 27. verſe vnto the end of the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> He is eaten in ſuche ſort, as he may be eaten: that is to ſay, ſpiritually by fayth: as the Lord hym ſelfe expoundeth this miſterie vnto vs at large, in <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> the ſixt chapter. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue the pureſt Doctours of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:16237:22"/> Church, taught any otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Yea, and this place may wel be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the woordes of the Supper of the Lord. For ſeeyng our Lord hath but one true bodye, the which he gaue vp to death for vs, &amp; that in theſe two places he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of this ſelfe ſame body, it ſeemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that this place of <hi>Saint Matthewe</hi> ought to be expounded by that of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> ſeeing that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> alſo in his third booke of the agreement of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes, ſuppoſeth that <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh not of the Inſtitution of the Supper of the Lord, becauſe in another place he had ſet foorth this matter at large. Al the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctours of the Church, ſpeaking of the Supper, allege the woords of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> and apply them to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, me thinketh,<note place="margin">The lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth himſefe.</note> that there cannot be found a better interpretour or expounder of the Lordes woord then the Lord himſelfe, who for ſo much as he ſaith in the .vi. Chapter of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> that his fleſh being eaten (to wit, corporally, as the Capernaites tooke it) profiteth
<pb facs="tcp:16237:23"/> nothing: It is moſt certayne, that hee would not geue in the .xxvi. of Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe</hi> that which profiteth nothing, and that he hath not ordayned here, that which he reiecteth and reprooueth there.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his true body at the ryght hand of the Father in heauen, maketh vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of lyfe, which he purchaſed for vs by giuing his body for vs, and by ſhedding his bloud) and we receyue the ſame lyfe of Chriſt, by true fayth, that is to wit, all the heauenly giftes of Chriſt, that Chriſt may lyue in vs, and we in him. And there is none other meane to receyue Chriſt, but by fayth. Euen as bodily foode cannot be taken to conſerue the bodyly lyfe, but by the mouth of the body: ſo ſpiritual foode, cannot otherwyſe be receyued of vs, to bring vs to the ſpirituall and eternall lyfe, but by the mouth of the ſoule, that is to ſay, by fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">We doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ache the bare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſtyng of bread.</note>Hereby all men may ſee, that we doo not acknowledge in any reſpect, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and prophane eating of bread, as ſome doo wrongfully charge vs. For we doo
<pb facs="tcp:16237:23"/> acknowledge and confeſſe Chriſt to be the meate and the drinke of lyfe, the which conceyue ſpiritually by fayth, as it hath been foreſhewed, not being able to eate him preſent, with the corporall mouth, carnally and corporally. We doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the faythfull are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt truly, and that they doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue him: And yet doo not the faythfull ſo reſtrayne or tye this partaking eyther to certayne tyme or element, as though they did not confeſſe, that it myght be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned without the Symboll or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>In both the two Sacramentes there is one reaſon of the communion of Chriſt, and in both the two, thoſe things, which Chriſt hath commaunded the faythfull to doo, are doone by them with a ſinguler profit. Therefore let no man eſteeme the vſe of the Sacramentes vayne or ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>Cornelius</hi> did not deſpyſe Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Act. 10.49.</note> or thinke it ſuperfluous, but he receyued it as the waſhing of regeneration, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that he did beleeue before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and had receyued the holy Ghoſt.
<pb facs="tcp:16237:24"/> Neither doo we receyue the Supper in vayne, when as we, proouing our ſelues (according to the commaundement of the Apoſtle) come to the Supper with fayth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> and euen with Ieſus Chriſt dwelling al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in our hartes.</p>
            <p>For in the celebration of the Supper, we continue the communion, which wee haue with him, in dooing (not without great ioye) that which the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to doo, in remembrance of him. And yet there is no doubt, but fayth oftentymes may be poured and geuen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the very celebration of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, vnto them which come thereunto, al though they be not ſo thorowly prepared, as it were meete they ſhould, that they may be made by the ſame fayth parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt. For who dare preſcribe or aſſigne vnto our ſo liberall a God, any tyme or meane?<note place="margin">There is a figure in the woordes of the Lords Supper.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore vtterly reiecting all carnall cogitation, let vs acknowledge that a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie is geuen here vnto vs. Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the holy Apoſtles and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes of the Lord haue in ſuch ſorte
<pb facs="tcp:16237:24"/> written the woordes touching the cuppe, that if any perhaps would tye himſelfe vnaduiſedly to the bare woordes touching the bread, and keepe himſelfe cloſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, he ſhould neuertheles be conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to come ſhort in the woordes touching the cuppe, and neceſſarily acknowledge a figure therein.</p>
            <p>Now is it meete to interpret the woords as wel of the bread as of the wine, with like obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. S. <hi>Matthew</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Marke</hi> cal the cup playnly <hi>Bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 26.28 Mark. 14.24.</note> 
               <hi>This (cuppe) is my bloud.</hi> Is the cuppe then deliuered vnto vs that we ſhould drinke it? No, ſay they, but the wine which is in the cuppe, the wyne is the bloud. I vnderſtand you wel: but I anſweare, that there is a figure, in that you ſay, that by the cuppe, we muſt vnderſtand the wyne which is in the cup. But if you vrge vs in theſe woordes,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26. Mark. 14.22 Luke. 22.19 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>this is my body,</hi> to reſt wholly in the literall ſenſe, what ſhould let vs to preſſe you alſo in the woordes of the cuppe, with the lyke literall ſenſe? But if you obiect vnto vs the abſurditie in theſe woordes, we will obiect to you the lyke abſurditie in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:16237:25"/> woordes alſo. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.25. Luke 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>This cuppe is the newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my bloud.</hi> What then? I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of you, whether the cuppe ſhall be the Teſtament? Who knoweth not, that the Teſtament or couenant is the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes? For the propheticall and Apoſtolicall Scripture dooth ſo witneſſe it alſo. How than? Shall the cuppe be rather within the bloud, than the bloud in the cuppe? Who is he I pray you, if he be not blinde, but he ſeeth here the figure. For the wine in the cuppe is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the true bloud of Chriſt, ſhedde for the remiſſion of ſinnes, the which commeth vnto vs by the teſtament.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay of that, which was forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Lawe, that the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, ſhould not eate of the<note place="margin">Leuit. 17.10.11.12.13. &amp; 14.</note> bloud of any oblation, whatſoeuer it were? who will then beleeue that in the moſt perfect Supper of the new Teſtament, we ſhould drinke bloud? If it were ſo, the <hi>Paynims</hi> long agoe ſayd truly, that the Chriſtians were woont in their aſſemblies to eate mans fleſh in deede, and to drynke bloud
<pb facs="tcp:16237:25"/> drawen from the very vaynes of men.<note place="margin">The Lord, as touching his body, hath left the earth, but he is preſent in ſpirit.</note> Moreouer, the auncient Chriſtians did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe myſteries ſpiritually. For me thinketh that the things, which wee haue touched, when as we are in hande with the doctrine of Chriſt in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ought here to be remembred. For the Lord hath no leſſe playnely expreſſed in the Supper the breade to be his body, than expreſly ſayd foorthwith after the Supper, that his body ſhould no longer be in the world, but that by his ſpirit hee would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with his vnto the worlds end: wherefore theſe woordes of the Lord pronounced in the Supper, and inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly after, ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred togeather. And that which more is, theſe woordes of the Lord:<note place="margin">Mark. 14.22 Mat. 26.26. Luk. 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>This is my body,</hi> be figuratiue and ſacramentall, but the other pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced after the Supper, be not figuratiue, neither haue any fruit or vſe in the church, if Chriſt remayn corporally in the church, hid vnder the kinde or, forme of bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe things ſayd I not vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>(ſayth he) at the beginning, bycauſe I was preſent with you, but now I goe my way to
<pb facs="tcp:16237:26"/> him that ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And agayne:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 16.7.</note>
               <hi>I tell you the truth, it is expedient for you, that I goe away: for if I goe not away, that Comforter will not come vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I went out from the Father and came into the worlde:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 16.28.</note> 
               <hi>agayne, I leaue the world, and goe to the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 17.11.</note>
               <hi>And now am I not in the world, and and they are in the world, and I come to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be they will ſay, that they will not affirme ſo groſſe a preſence of Chriſt in the Supper: Let them then ſhewe, what manner of preſence it is, which they doo affirme. Surely they will ſay, that they vnderſtand a corporall preſence, but yet notwithſtanding ſpirituall, inuiſible, and ineffable. But the body of Chriſt is, and abideth a true body,<note place="margin">The vnitie of the perſon of Chriſt doth not take awaye the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the natures.</note> and is not conuerted or changed into a ſpirit, although it be glorified. It is very true, that it is ioyned to the diuinitie in vnitie of perſon, yet the natures neuertheleſſe abide whole, and not confounded. Therefore all the auncient
<pb facs="tcp:16237:26"/> true, and catholike doctors cry euery one with one conſent: <hi>Chriſt very God and very Man, is one Chriſt, who is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, but the properties of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures remayne in him whole: in ſuch ſorte, that as hee is God, hee is euerye where, and as he is Man, he is in one certayne place of heauen, and not euery where, ſauing onely according to the communication of the properties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſequently they accurſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt as accurſed, all ſuch which thinke the contrary. It followeth therefore hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, that there can none other ſpirituall meanes be eſtabliſhed in the Supper, but that, whereby Chriſt our Lord (which hath and retayneth a true body, and is reſident in heauen) is preſent vnto vs by his holy ſpirit, reuiueth vs, feedeth vs, refreſheth vs, and ſaueth vs: and this vertue is diuine and aboue other moſt excellent, and not a thing voyde and vayne.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe it is not neceſſary, that in treating of the Lords Supper, wee ſhould diſpute of the corporall preſence of Chriſt in the Supper, and of the carnall
<pb facs="tcp:16237:27"/> eating of his body, and yet ineffable, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that our Supper is myſticall, and not capernaycall (that I ſay no more) the which if it were carnall, myght be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for contraryly if it cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it cannot be called corporall. Let it not therefore be denied agayne, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready is agreed vpon.</p>
            <p>Therefore the auncient miniſters of the Church, were accuſtomed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Supper to cry to the people: <hi>Lift vp your hartes.</hi> Whereunto in like manner the ſaying of the Apoſtle may be applyed: when as he ſayth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.3. and 4.</note>
               <hi>Our Fathers did all eate of the ſame ſpirituall meate: and did all drinke of the ſame ſpirituall drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which we reade in the .x. Chapter of the fyrſt to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the reſt, wee will ſpeake ſome other tyme how the vnfaythfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing partakers of the ſymboll and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not of the thing, which it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, eat and drinke their iudgement and condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeuenth</note>The Lord in like manner tooke the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:27"/> cuppe after ſupper,<note place="margin">Article. He offereth alſo vnto vs the cuppe.</note> and diſtributed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all. For he ſhedde his bloud for them all. And as he is the meate of al, ſo is he alſo the drinke of all. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayd he playnly: <hi>Drinke ye all of it.</hi> And in like manner <hi>S. Marke</hi> affirmeth that they alſo did, ſaying:<note place="margin">Mark. 14.23 Mark. 24.24.</note> 
               <hi>And they all dranke of it.</hi> Let then the decrees and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of all men whatſoeuer, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that the lay or ſecular ſhould communicate at the Supper, vnder one of the two kindes onely (that is to ſay, vnder the forme of breade) giue place to theſe cleare and expreſſe woordes of the Lord. Now as he declared before, what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner bread it was, which he gaue to his, ſo dooth he here in lyke manner ſhew, what manner cuppe or wine this is,<note place="margin">Math. 26.27.</note> that is to ſay, ſacramentall. <hi>This is my bloud, (ſayth he) of the new testament,</hi> or,<note place="margin">Luke 22.20. 1. Cor. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>This cuppe is the newe Testament in my bloud.</hi> We haue declared before, that in this ſpeech there is a figure. For the chalice or the cuppe is the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bloud of Chriſt, by the which bloud the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is conſecrated and dedicated, and
<pb facs="tcp:16237:28"/> by the which we haue obtayned remiſſion of ſinnes. We drinke therefore ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the bloud of the Lord by fayth, as we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo eate his body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſignes and ſeales of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>Furthermore theſe Sacramentes or ſymbols, ſerue vs for a ſeale and for a true teſtimonie, that the ſonne of God, hauyng take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> humane fleſh, is come into the world, who hauyng gyuen his body, and ſhed his bloud, hath fully redemed his electe, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyllyng all thinges promiſed and written in the lawe and Prophetes. The which matter <hi>Sainct Paul</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> doth more at larg expounde vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The Lorde addeth herevnto:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.25.</note>
               <hi>So often as you do this, do it in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Sainct Paull</hi> ſayth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.26.</note>
               <hi>Ye do ſhewe the Lordes death till he come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The eyght Article. The celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſupper is free.</note>This ſentence teacheth vs three thinges. Firſt, that it is lawfull for the Church of Chriſte, To celebrate this Supper, ſo often as it will, and that it is not bound, or ſubiecte to any certayne number. And
<pb facs="tcp:16237:28"/> for this cauſe, the ſentence of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> to <hi>Ianuarius</hi> is commendable: The which he vttereth thus: <hi>Some will ſay, That we ought to receyue the communion eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and other will ſay the contrary. But he reconcyleth them well, which admoniſheth them to continue eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the peace of Chriſt. Let euery one do that, which he beleeueth Godly according to his fayth, that he ought to do. For neyther of them both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoureth the body and bloud of the Lorde. This foode may no wyſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſequently the ende of the Supper is ſhewed, when as it is not once only,<note place="margin">The ſupper is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of Chriſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>and</hi> 25.</note> but often tymes repeated: <hi>This do ye in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of me.</hi> For the Lorde by the holy aſſembly of his people, and by this action (the which after a ſorte ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, yea and layeth playnely before our eyes theſe things to be loked vpon by vs,) woulde that we ſhoulde retayne, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printe in our memorie, this great benefite and miſtery of our redemption, and of his paſſion, that is to ſay, that he had delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:16237:29"/> his body to death for vs, and ſhed his bloud for the remiſſion of our ſinnes, and gyuen them vs alſo in meate and drinke for our ſaluation. Wherfore in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the bread and wyne, we muſt not ſtay our ſelues only in the beholdyng of them, but we muſt beholde the thinges which they repreſente vnto vs, that is to ſay, the paſſion of the Lorde, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>Our Lorde came once into the earthe, he died once, and hath purged and clenſed vs all: Afterwarde he aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, from thence he ſhall not come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he come to iudge the worlde: Alſo our Lorde ſhall dye no more, he died once, but his only death hath ſtrength and efficacy for euer. And the Lorde worketh in vs through his holy ſpirite ſanctification and lyfe.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, theſe thinges which we do, ſerue vs for remembraunces, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunces (I ſay) inſtituted touching thinges paſt, to confirme &amp; refreſhe often tymes the remembraunce of the paſſion of the Lord, and of our redemption. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:16237:29"/> the ſaying of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> agaynſt a <hi>Manichee</hi> is prayſe worthy. <hi>The fleſhe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and the bloud of this ſacrifice, were promiſed before the comyng of Chriſt, by the oblations and offeringes, Which were figures of them, in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, they were perfourmed by the trulie it ſelfe: and after the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">You ſhall ſhew the death of the Lord.</note> 
               <hi>they are celebrated by the ſacrament of the memoriall.</hi> Lo what he ſayth hereof. Now the ſame Lorde in aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tyme ordained the Paſcall Supper, which he called alſo a memoriall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration, that the benefit of the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce foorth of Egypte (the true image and figure of the vniuerſall redemption by Chriſt) might be refreſhed and renued e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery yere to the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. There was meate in both the two, there were great benefites in both two, but yet the truth is here in the Supper, &amp; the ſhadow in the other, in both two the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, in both two ſaluation, and lyfe, through the Meſſias, finally in both two there were prayſes, and ſpirituall reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng. For in the Supper we are commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:16237:30"/> to ſhewe the death of the Lord: which in deede is nothyng els, but the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to yeelde prayſe, and thankeſgiuyng to the Lorde for his death. And ſo this parte, whereof we haue heretofore ſpoken, is agayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, and for this cauſe we are often put in remembraunce thereof, as of that thing, which is not the leaſt in that holy bankquet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ninth Article. Vntill he come.</note>Now we are commaunded to do theſe thinges, vntill he come, That is to ſay, vntill the Lorde returne in Iudgement. All the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the auncient fathers were inſtituted vntil the tyme of correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is to ſay, vntill the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of Chriſt, who by hys commyng into the worlde, hath fulfilled al the promyſes, hauyng ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated and aboliſhed the ſhadowes and figures. Therfore hath he now inſtituted this ſacrament, that it might be perpetual and immutable, That is to ſay, that it might indure in the Churche, vntill the Lorde returne in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fully to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh that, which he promiſed by his word. Who is he than, that dare chaunge it? If
<pb facs="tcp:16237:30"/> any haue bene ſo holde to make any ſuch chaunge, who is he, which ſeeth not, how greately he hath ſinned agaynſt God, and how vnworthy he is, that we ſhoulde heare him?</p>
            <p>By theſe thinges we are confirmed to continue in this ſimplicity, keepyng our ſelues from receyuing at the handes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon, whatſoeuer he be, any thing, which agreeth not with this inſtitution and holy maner of doyng. Let the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt ſuffice vs, let vs here do ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that, which the Lorde hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to do, hauyng herein ſet foorth him ſelfe to vs, for an example and guyde.</p>
            <p>It reſteth that we declare in two woordes,<note place="margin">What kind of men the Apoſtles were in the ſupper.</note> what manner of men the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Lorde were in this Supper, &amp; how they behaued them ſelues therein, that hereby we may learne, how we ought to behaue our ſelues alſo in the celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this moſt holy banquet. True it is, that they were weake and ſinners, the which they well declared in the Supper by certayne tokens. Neuertheleſſe they beleeued by true fayth in the Lorde, were
<pb facs="tcp:16237:31"/> receyued into his fauour, and clenſed from their ſinnes, they acknowledged theyr weakeneſſe, made theyr ſupplication to the Lord, depended vppon him only, and obeyed him ſimply in all, and through all, ſubmitting them ſelues to him, and doing ſimply in the Supper al that which he commaunded them. And the Apoſtles were not defiled by the preſence of <hi>Iudas</hi> the traytor, for they were farre from his conditions. Therfore leaſt no man thinke himſelfe defiled, when he ſeeth in the Supper the wicked and profane receiue it, but let him take heede, that he him ſelfe be not wicked. Euery one ſhal beare his owne burden.</p>
            <p>Let vs followe in all things the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Lord, in ſimplicitie, fayth and obedience, dooing that, which they did, following the commaundement of the Lord, beleeuing that we are acceptable to the father through Ieſus Chriſt, of whom only it behoueth vs to depend, beſeeching him to abſolue vs, to make vs perfect, and to conſerue vs. To him be glory for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16237:31"/>
            <p>To fill vp theſe leaues, we haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hereunto this notable place of Saint <hi>Vigilius</hi> the Martyr foorth of his firſt boke againſt hereſies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſeemeth to me, that they are ſo couered and blinded with the vayle of treaſon and falſehood, that they can neither ſee, nor vnderſtand, that one thing agreeth to the diuinitie of Chriſt, another thing to his humanitie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be in like ſort common to both the two.</hi> For he ſayth to his Diſciples: <hi>If ye loued me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>ye would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely reioyce, bycauſe I ſayd, I go vnto the Father, for the Father is greater then I.</hi> And againe:<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>It is expedient for you, that I goe away: for if I goe not away, that comforter will not come vnto you. <hi>And vndoubtedly the woorde of God, the vertue of God, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, hath been alway with the father, and in the father, euen then alſo when it was in vs and with vs. For in that tyme, when by his mercie hee dwelled vppon earth, he forſooke not his heauenly dwelling. For with the
<pb facs="tcp:16237:32"/> Father he is all in all places, of equall Godhead, and no place can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende him: For all things are filled with the Sonne, and there is no place voyde of the preſence of his Godhead. Wherefore then, and why ſayth hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne or how dooth he affirme, that he will goe to the Father, from whom vndoubtedly he neuer departed? But to goe to the Father and to depart from vs, was to take foorth of this world the nature, which he had taken of vs. Thou ſeeſt therefore, that it was proper to the ſelfe ſame nature, to be taken hence, and to depart from vs, the which in the end of times, muſt be reſtored to vs agayne, according to the witneſſe geuen by the voyce of the Angels: <hi>This Ieſus, which is taken vp from you into heauen,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 1.11. Matt. 28.20.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall ſo come, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as you haue ſeene him goe into heauen.</hi> wherefore behold the miracle, behold the miſterie, and the ſecrete of the two properties: The Sonne of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from vs according to his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, but according to his Godhead
<pb facs="tcp:16237:32"/> he ſayth: <hi>I am with you alway, vnto the end of the world.</hi> If he be with vs, how ſayth he: <hi>The dayes will come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 17.22.</note> 
                  <hi>when ye ſhall deſire to ſee one day of the Sonne of man, and ye ſhall not ſee it?</hi> But he is with vs, and he is not with vs. For theſe, whom he hath left, and from whom he is departed touching his Manhead, he hath not left, neither is he departed from. Touching his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. For by the forme of a ſeruant, which he hath caried from vs into heauen, he is abſent from vs: but by the forme of God, which dooth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from vs, he is preſent with vs in earth: notwithſtanding both preſent and abſent, he is vnto vs, one and the ſelfe ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London, nigh vnto the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawſon <hi>and Thomas Gardyner, for Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Ponſonby.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
